Finding Aid for the A. Conger Goodyear War of 1812 Manuscripts, 1779-1862
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
A. Conger Goodyear War of 1812 Manuscripts
1779 - 1862
Mss. B00-11
Goodyear, A. Conger (Anson Conger), 1877-1964
4 boxes (2 linear feet)
Papers pertaining to the War of 1812.
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
The A. Conger Goodyear War of 1812 Manuscripts, 1779-1862, are open for research.
Researchers wishing to access this collection must apply for a Scholar Pass and present valid photo ID upon arrival to the library.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
The War of 1812 Manuscripts were donated by A. Conger Goodyear.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
Microfilm copy available ( M2008-1 ).
Biographical Note
Anson Conger Goodyear was born to a prominent family in Buffalo, New York in June 20, 1877. After he graduated from Yale in 1899, he began working in his family's lumber business and became president of the firm in 1911. His interests extended beyond his family firm to include railroads, serving as vice-president of the Buffalo and Susquehanna Railroad between 1907 and 1910, and president of the New Orleans Great Northern Railroad Company from 1920 to 1930.
Goodyear was also known for a patron of the fine arts and collector. Goodyear succeeded his father as a director of the Buffalo Academy of Fine Arts and was appointed in 1929 as the first president of The Museum of Modern Art in New York City. He served in that position until 1939 when he was succeeded by Nelson A. Rockefeller. Goodyear continued serving on the acquisitions committee until the 1950s and remained a trustee of the Museum until his death on April 24, 1964.
Serving in both World Wars I and II, he ended his service with the rank of major general. In 1955 Goodyear received the chancellor's Medal from the University of Buffalo for his contribution to the Lockwood Library Collection.
Modified from Biographical note, MoMA The Museum of Fine Art and Buffalo News (08/09/1951 and 04/24/1964), University Archives, University at Buffalo, The State University of New York.
Scope and Content Note
Miscellaneous War of 1812 manuscripts collected by A. Conger Goodyear, including orderly books of camps Batavia and Buffalo; memoranda from an original journal by Gen. Jacob Brown, 1814; letterbooks of Amos Hall and Roger Hale Sheaffe; and letters, documents and maps concerning the Porter- Smyth controversy, the Battle of Black Rock and the destruction of Buffalo, and the battles of Chippewa, Queenstown, Lundy's Lane, Lake Erie, and Fort Erie. Writers include Peter B. Porter and Stephen Van Rensselaer.
Manuscripts mounted in bound volumes originally collected by Benson J. Lossing; purchased by A. Conger Goodyear.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by volume.
Container List
- Sir Roger Hale Sheaffe: Letterbook, October 1812-April 1818 (Box-folder 1.1, Volume 1)
  Contains copies of letters to and from Sheaffe from the time he assumed command until April 13, 1813, with several letters written after the close of the war. Commander of British troops after the fall of Brock at Queenstown.
- Typed copies of selected Letters of Sir Roger Hale Sheaffe, undated (Box-folder 1.2)
- Typed copies of selected Letters of Sir Roger Hale Sheaffe, undated (Box-folder 1.3)
- Typed copies of selected Letters of Sir Roger Hale Sheaffe, undated (Box-folder 1.4)
- Orderly book, April 6-July 14, 1814 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  Includes given passwords, officers of the day, and other regimental details; dated from Camp Batavia and Camp Buffalo.
- Memoranda of occurrences &c connected with the Campaign of Niagara, 1814 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  Probably copied from an original journal of "Genl. JACOB BRONN." Entries cover the investment of Fort Erie (2 July), Battle of Lundy's Lane (25 July) and the sortie from Fort Erie (17 September). Also copies of correspondence with the Secretary of War and others, 1814-1825, and an estimate of the size and distribution of British troops in Upper Canada, 1 July 1814.
- Major -General AMOS HALL: Letterbook, May-October 1812. (Box 1, Volume 4)
  Includes miscellaneous notes on American Indians.
- Orderly book, April-August, 1814. (Box 2, Volume 5)
  Probably the original orderly book of General Jacob Brown for the Niagara Campaign.
- Battle of Black Rock/Destruction of Buffalo, 1813 (Box 2, Volume 6)
  Includes two manuscript narratives (anonymous, undated) of the fall of Fort George (27 May, 1813) and the destruction of Buffalo (29-30 December, 1813); and a manuscript narrative by Peter B. Porter describing the Battle of Black Rock (11 July, 1813).
- Porter-Smyth Controversy, undated (Box 2, Volume 7)
  Includes five letters Peter B. Porter, John Levett, and General Solomon Van Rensselaer concerning the case of General Alexander Smyth; and one letter dated Mount Hope, 7 January, 1813, stating the circumstances of his duel with Peter B. Porter.
- Battle of Queenstown, 1812, 1822-1824 (Box 2, Volume 8)
  Includes six letters by Stephen Van Rensselaer, Solomon Van Rensselaer, H.B. Armstrong, Nicholas Gray, and Thomas Cooper concerning the battle of Queenstown, 1812 and political affairs, 1822-1824.
- Armstrong -Brown - Wilkinson - War of 1812, 1813-1836 (Box 3, Volume 9)
  Includes a letter signed by General Jacob Brown (1813), General James Wilkinson (1814), General John Armstrong (1814,1836) and Thomas H. Blake (1814); also portraits of Brown, Wilkinson, Izard and Armstrong.
- Battle of Lake Erie, 1813 Ms. Accounts, undated (Box 3, Volume 10)
  Includes retrospective narratives of the Battle of Lake Erie by Usher Persons (1860), Ezekiel Fowler (1852) arid John Chapman (1853); and three letters by Stephen Champlin (1862), Jesse Elliot (undated.), and Isaac Chauncey (1826)
- Usher Parsons: Diary, November 1812-December 1814 (Box 3, Volume 11)
  Includes additional memoranda concerning the history of the Lake Erie squadron, etc, and 11 pages of clippings pasted in; a letter from Parsons to Lossing, 17 February 1860, is laid in. Parsons, surgeon on Oliver Hazard Perry's flagship "Lawrence," copied these diary entries for the historian Benson J. Lossing in 1860.
- Veterans Correspondence regarding "War of 1812", 1779-1854 (Box 3, Volume 12)
  Includes 63 manuscripts concerning the War of 1812, or written by veterans of the war.
  Varum, Joseph B., Jr.
  Sackets Harbor, April 26,1814 regarding War of 1812
  Sackets Harbor, May 1,1814 regarding War of 1812
  Utica, May 24,1814 regarding War of 1812
  Utica, May 31, 1814 regarding War of 1812
  Headquarters near Chipaway, July 7,1814 regarding War of 1812
  Buffalo, July 24,1814
  (Marked: "Received August 10") regarding War of 1812
  Buffalo, August.11,1814
  New York, October.9,1815 regarding business dealings
  New York, November 8,1815 regarding money owed him
  New York, December 12,1815 regarding Apothecary Dept. of Army
  Unknown author, letter to Adjunct General (John) Brooke (Adjunct General of Massachusetts 1812-15 and governor 1816-23), dated Boston Sept.16,1814, regarding using a house for hospital, medicines, etc. for sick soldiers.
  Appleton, (Honorable) William (Autograph only).
  Barber, (Honorable) John S. A.L.S. Catalpa, June 10,1829 to Major W.B. Lewis stating that he expects to hear from Mr.Madison.
  Invoice of merchandise shipped at Marseilles on board the Brig. Nancy, Glover Broughton, Master August 13,1823.
  Invoice of sugar and hides shipped on Sloop Polly P. Trasher dated Marblehead Oct. 6,1826 for account and risk of N.& G. Broughton & Kennedy, consigned to N. Broughton.
  Invoice of merchandise shipped at Manilla by N. Broughton on board the ship Java dated :Manilla July 4,1821
  Invoice of merchandise shipped on Schooner Speedwell, Glover Broughton, Master dated, March 10,1822.
  Invoice of corks shipped at Marseilles Brig Nancy G. Broughton, Master dated August 13,1823.
  Invoice of Brazilian produce shipped on board Brig Nancy by Glover Broughton, Master for account of Mr. Sam Fortune, July 24, 1825, Sale of Brazilian produce for account of Mr. Sam Fortune.
  Invoice of dry salted hides shipped on board Brig Nancy by G. Broughton the master for Mr. Sam Fortune, M. Mead dated September 20, 1825.
  Account of Mr. Sam Fortune with Glover Broughton dated September 20,1825.
  Invoice of sugar shipped on board the Brig Nancy, Glover Broughton, Master, for Nicholas Broughton.
  Butler, John, (Captain)-Return of forage for 59 horses of Butler's troop of U.S. Lt. Dragoons, June 7-30,1813
  Cooper, John T. (General War of 1812) autograph letter signed, Albany April 2, 1849 to President & Directors, Albany Gas Company
  Gibson, John. (Quartermaster General, So.Div.) autograph letter signed New Orleans, April 3,1817 to His Excellency David Holmes, Governor Mississippi Territory regarding payment of old claims.
  Glen, John V. to Honorable H. Bleecker, Representative in the Congress of the United States, autograph letter signed July 15,1812; stating that if he fails to receive appointment in Regular Service he desires appointment in Volunteers.
  Autograph letter signed. August 7, 1812 mentions that nomination was withdrawn, asks for explanation.
  Autograph letter signed, January 20, 1813 requesting "something explanatory in the defeats of my appointment..."
  Autograph letter signed, October l, 1814, offering himself for service in Corps of Regulars and Minute Men to be raised for protection of Frontiers.
  Goldsborough, C.(harles) Autograph letter signed Washington August 1, 1813 to Harmanus Bleecker, Esquire, Albany, New York, mentions devastations along Potomac river.
  Autograph letter signed, Cambridge December 9, 1813 mentions his late return to Washington and states "You know that my disposition as a politician has not generally been that of despondency; but I must confess so gloomy do our prospects appear & so distressing have been my anticipations for some time past, that I have endeavored to shut my mind as much as possible against political contemplations." He mentions the failure of the Canada campaign and possible court materials.
  Granger, Amos P. Autograph letter signed. Syracuse, New York, October 18, 1852 to Simon Draper regarding publicity in Irishman for election. (A notation on reverse, S. Draper to Mr. Greeley)
  Hayne, A. P. Autograph letter singed. New York October. 23, 1852 to Major Lloyd J. Beale, Albany, New York re-shipment of horses by steamer.
  Huntington, Gurdon, Autograph letter signed. January 4, 1814 to Messrs. Walter and Geo. Weed, merchants, Albany regarding debt owed to them.
  Autograph letter signed, May 26,1814, sending additional payment on account.
  King, William- Autograph document signed. Fish Kill Landing April 1,1779 certificate that Capt. Ten Eyck and four hands were victualed at post up to and including the 30th inst. (Short typewritten biography of William King, Colonel of United States Army)
  Knickerbacker, H. Autograph letter signed. Washington City December 25, 1809 to Messrs. Bleecker and Sedgwyck, Albany regarding an impending war with G. Britain
  Lamb, Anthony (aid de camp) Doc.S., General Orders, Headquarters Albany, June 10, 1811 regarding organization of 3rd brigade of Cavalry to be commanded by John I. Van Rensselaer.
  Lovett, John Autograph letter signed. December 16, 1810 to H. Bleecker, Esquire, Albany regarding sending copies of Laws of last session.
  Autograph letter signed. Washington, December 16, 1813 to H. Bleecker, Esquire, stating his political view, etc.
  Autograph letter signed. Washington Sunday evening 16th October ,1814 regarding politics.
  Laurence, John Autograph letter signed. Newark, New Jersey, August 26, 1806 to James Greenleaf re papering 2 rooms, etc.
  Leonard, N(athaniel) Captain. Comg. Fort Niagara April 1812 monthly return of the Garrison.
  Leonard N(athaniel) Captain Comg. Fort Niagara December 31, 1810- "Return of Ordinance and Military Stores at Fort Niagara"
  [Macomb, Alexander]- Formal invitation of General and Mrs. Macomb to Major (W.B) Lewis Jan. 15 (no year)
  Mason, J. (General) 2 letters to Joseph Wilson, C. of the port at Marblehead regarding American prisoners of war, signed, Office of Commissary-General of Prisoners, Washington, November 13, 1813 and February 11 ,1814
  McCulloch, Ben. Autograph letter to William B. Lewis re payment for service of horses and wagon, signed, May 1, 1814
  Mooers, Benj. (Major General) Autograph letter to Governor Tompkins, reporting calling of all militia for the defense of Plattsburgh. Accompanied by a short field report of movements of the enemy, signed Plattsburgh, September 4, 1814
  Nicholl, A.Y. (Adjutant General) Autograph endorsement listing promotions in the Army by the President with the consent of the Senate, signed Washington, May 3, 1810
  Ogden, Francis B. Certification of affidavit of Edward Akroyd signed Liverpool, February 13, 1840.
  Certification of affidavit of Edward Akroyd signed by Pearce for Ogden, Liverpool, June 7, 1839
  P(omeroy) J. Autograph letter, regarding Clinton, Fremont, etc., initialed to Honorable Harm Bleecker, Stockbridge November 26, 1812,
  Reed, William 5 Autograph letters signed to Honorable Harmanus Bleecker, 1814-1829
  Washington, February 1, 1814, regarding War of 1812, politics, etc. Boston, November 22,1819 invitation to dinner.
  Marblehead, July 23,1829 personal letter re religious sentiments.
  Marblehead, August 10, 1824 introducing his nephew, Mr.B. J. Reed, Jr.
  Marblehead, November 30, 1825 invitation to Bleecker and Mr. Kane to visit the Reed's.
  Autograph letter unsigned (Frank showing signature of W. Reed) to Honorable Harmanus Bleecker regarding bank bill before Congress.
  Robinson, J.E. Autograph letter to Elisha Tibbits regarding inability to collect debt of I.& S. Wright because of military service, etc., signed July 19, 1813
  Sutherland, Joel B. Autograph letter to Major William B. Lewis regarding Senate action on Mr. Tyson, signed Philadelphia, March 13, 1842
  Autograph letter signed Philadelphia February 28,(no year) to Major Wm.B.Lewis re passing of law relative to at large appointments.
  Autograph letter unsigned dated October 10,1834 regarding transfer of Colonel Miller of Marine Corps
  Tallmadge, James Autograph letter to Thurlow Weed introducing Rufus Fancher, signed Poughkeepsie, September 28,1825
  Whittlesey, Elisha Autograph letter to Phillip R. Fendall sending copy of a letter from Honnorable James Guthrie, signed November 30,1854
- Battle of Chippewa, 1814 1814-1840 (Box 3, Volume 13)
  Includes one manuscript narrative and two autograph letters signed by Peter B. Porter concerning the Battle of Chippewa.
- Thomas S. Jesup: "Memoir of the Campaign on the Niagara," July 1814 (Box 4, Volume 14)
  Includes narrative of the events in the Niagara campaign, from the Battle of Chippewa (5 July 1814) to the Battle of Niagara (25 July 1814).
- "Battle of hundy's Lane, 1814-Leavenworth" 1814 (Box 4, Volume 15)
  Includes miscellaneous maps, documents, and letters from 1808 to1860, a contemporary manuscript account by Colonel Henry Leavenworth and autograph letter signed by Ben Winfield Scott.
- Battles of Fort Erie and Niagara, 1814, undated (Box 4, Volume 16)
  Includes two autograph letters signed by Brig. General James Miller and Adjutant General Edward Baynes, 1814; ADS of Peter B. Porter, 1814; and map ("Siege and Defense of Fort Erie" ).
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Brown, Jacob, 1775-1828; Sheaffe, Roger Hale, b. 1763; Porter, Peter B. (Peter Buell), 1773-1844; Van Rensselaer, Stephen, 1764-1839; Smyth, Alexander, 1765-1830; Hall, Amos, fl. 1812; Buffalo History Museum
Subject Terms
United States--History--War of 1812
Genre Terms
Autographs (manuscripts); Correspondence; Reminiscences